Guide to the Frederic Ewen Audiotape and Videotape Collection OH.052
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frederic Ewen Audiotape and Videotape Collection
1954-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ewen, Frederic, 1899-
OH.052
10.5 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
Frederic Ewen was an English professor at Brooklyn College from 1930 until 1952, when he accepted early retirement rather than cooperate with the McCarran Committee’s investigation of communism in higher education. He went on to lecture and write books and articles on literary topics. In the 1950s and 60s he organized several series of theatrical lectures and performances, many of them featuring blacklisted actors; recordings of some of the presentations are found in this collection. The Ewen Audio/Video Collection also contains more than 30 interviews with teachers affected by the investigations of the New York State Legislature’s Rapp-Coudert Committee; these were collected under the rubric of the Frederic Ewen Academic Freedom Collection, now based at New York University.
Provenance
The Frederic Ewen Audiotape and Videotape Collection was donated to the Tamiment Library with the Frederic Ewen Papers in 1999 by his grandson, Alex Ewen. Included were ten linear feet transferred from Brooklyn College, where they had been housed for some time. The donation of the collection marked the establishment of the Frederic Ewen Academic Freedom Collection at the Tamiment Library, New York University with financial support from Ewen’s nephew, Herbert Kurz.
An additional interview with Bernard Grebanier from 1974 was donated by Marvin Gettleman in 2009 and added to the collection.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Historical/Biographical Note
Frederic Ewen was an author, educator, and champion of the individual's right to self-expression and intellectual freedom. A popular lecturer at Brooklyn College, where he was Assistant Professor of English Literature, he dedicated his final book to his former students, who for him had made "teaching a privilege and learning a joy." Dr. Ewen's political activism during the 1930s and thereafter led to his becoming a victim of the academic witch-hunts of the McCarthy Era, and his forced retirement from Brooklyn College in 1952.
Frederic Ewen was born on October 11, 1899, in Lembert, Austria, the son of Isaac and Helen (Kramer) Ewen. He was brought by his family to the United States in 1912 and became a naturalized citizen that same year. Ewen grew up in Brooklyn and then attended City College, where he graduated in 1921; he then attended Columbia University, where he received his M.A. degree in 1925 and completed his Ph.D. in English and Comparative Literature in 1932. He began his career as a teacher at City College, starting as an English instructor in 1923. In 1930 he began teaching English at Brooklyn College, and eventually attained the rank of assistant professor. An activist in many progressive causes in the 1930s, Ewen was in demand as a political speaker. On campus his political activities included serving as advisor to a student Marxist society, helping to organize support for the Spanish Republic during the Spanish Civil War, and participating in work of the New York Teachers Union.
Established in 1940, and functioning mostly in 1941-42, the New York State Legislature's Joint Committee to Investigate Procedure and Methods of Allocating State Moneys for Public School Purposes and Subversive Activities, known as the Rapp-Coudert Committee, investigated allegations of subversive activities in the New York City's public schools and colleges. Along with seven other teachers from Brooklyn College, Dr. Ewen refused to testify before the Committee's representatives, calling the investigation an "attack on the things that the system stands for and had fought in the last 20 years to obtain." Although Dr. Ewen and other tenured Brooklyn College professors were spared the fate suffered by a group of their colleagues at City College who were investigated and dismissed (or pressured to resign) by the Board of Higher Education, Dr. Ewen and other progressive teachers at Brooklyn suffered professionally, and fell under suspicion again during the anti-subversive hysteria of the early 1950s.
In addition to his teaching, Dr. Ewen was a noted author. His first book, The Prestige of Schiller in England, was published in 1932; three years later his Bibliography of Eighteenth-Century English Literature followed. Musical Vienna, which he co-wrote with his brother, was published in 1939 and The Poetry and Prose of Heinrich Heine was published in 1948. In 1949 Ewen married Miriam Gideon, a composer.
In 1952 Ewen was called to testify before the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee (known as the McCarran Committee), and he knew that non-cooperation would mean the loss of his job. Because of his long service he was eligible for early retirement, and he felt obliged to accept that alternative; his retirement took effect the day before his scheduled testimony. Appearing before the Committee's representatives, he stood on his Fifth Amendment rights and refused to testify. Dr. Ewen's wife, Miriam Gideon, a composer who also taught (in an untenured position) at Brooklyn College, lost her position as well, and in order to support his family he organized lectures and theatrical presentations in union halls, theaters and other venues in the 1950s and 1960s. Gathering a team of blacklisted actors who were in need of work, such as Ossie Davis, Ruby Dee, and John Randolph, Dr. Ewen created a novel form of public performance, in which he lectured on a particular author or literary/dramatic theme, and the actors read excerpts from the relevant works. Television adaptations by Ewen include "Two Jewish Stories" in 1966, "The Unknown Chekhov" in 1967, and Chekhov's "Ward Number 6" in 1968, all done for CBS.
In 1967, Citadel Press published Dr. Ewen's Bertolt Brecht: His Life, His Art, and His Times. Over the next 20 years, Professor Ewen worked on other publishing projects. The first volume of his projected trilogy on the literature and politics of the mid-nineteenth century, was published by Citadel in 1984 as Heroic Imagination: The Creative Genius of Europe from Waterloo to the Revolution of 1848. Ewen's introduction to The Collected Short Stories of Maxim Gorky appeared in the month of his death, October 1988.
Frederic Ewen died on October 18, 1988, in Manhattan. In 1981, first the City College Faculty Senate and then the CUNY Faculty Senate passed a resolution (composed by Steve Leberstein) apologizing formally to the victims of the Rapp-Coudert investigations. In 1988, after Ewen's death, a lecture series bearing his name was established at Brooklyn College. In subsequent years the Frederic Ewen Academic Freedom Center was established with financial support from Ewen's nephew, Herbert Kurz. First based at Brooklyn College, the project was relocated as the Frederic Ewen Academic Freedom Collection at New York University's Tamiment Library. At its 75th anniversary commencement in June 2005, Brooklyn College presented a special Presidential Citation to Ewen's family; the citation recognized Frederic Ewen's accomplishments as a scholar and a teacher, and noted his "impassioned defense of liberty and intellectual freedom."
Scope and Content Note
The Collection consists of Ewen's personal audiotape collection and a collection of oral histories with teachers and others affected by the Rapp-Coudert investigation and later blacklisting efforts. Because the videotaped interviews with these teachers so closely relate to the audiotaped interviews, the Tamiment Library has housed them in the same collection.
Part 1: Reference Copies. Series I: Interviews Relating to Rapp-Coudert Committee Investigations and Blacklisting includes over 30 interviews with teachers who were investigated by the Rapp-Coudert Committee, as well as a few interviews with actors and performers who were blacklisted in the McCarthy era. Frederic Ewen's grandson, Alex Ewen, conducted the majority of these interviews in 1990 on behalf of the Frederic Ewen Center for Academic Freedom Oral History Project. Other interviews are by Steven Leberstein, Barbara Caress and Ellen W. Schrecker. The interviews are in audiocassette tape and Hi-8 videotape format, with 15 accompanying transcripts.
Part I, Series II: Public Lectures and Performances consists of recordings of public lectures, dramatic readings and performances presented and organized by Ewen held in the 1950s and 60s; many of these feature blacklisted actors. The recordings include performances by Ruby Dee, Ossie Davis, John Randolph and Sarah Cunningham. (The Frederic Ewen Papers at the Tamiment Library include many programs and flyers that describe these performances in detail. See: Related Materials.)
Part 1, Series III: Readings by Frederic Ewen includes Ewen's private readings recorded on audiocassette tapes in the last two decades of his life. In these years, Ewen read and took notes on a vast number of books and literary works, and recorded passages from many books and his comments about them on tape.
Part 2: Duplicates and Archival Masters. For access consult with archives staff.
Arrangement
In Part 1, Series I and III are arranged alphabetically and Series II is arranged chronologically. In Part 2 materials are grouped into series by format, and within each series the tapes follow the sequence established in Part 1.
Part 1: Reference Copies. Series I: Interviews relating to Rapp-Coudert Committee Investigations and Blacklisting; Series II: Public Lectures and Performances; and Series III: Readings by Frederic Ewen. Part 2: Duplicate Copies and Archival Masters of Tapes in Part 1 (For Access Consult Archives Staff). Series I: Audiocassette Tapes; Series II: Reel-to-Reel Tapes; Series III: Digital Audiotapes (DAT); Series IV: Archival Masters (Reel-to-Reel Tapes).
Missing Title
Part I: Series I: Interviews relating to Rapp-Coudert Committee Investigations and Blacklisting
Part I: Series II: Public Lectures and Performances
Part I: Series III: Readings by Frederic Ewen.
Part 2: Series I: Audiocassette Tapes
Part 2: Series II: Reel-to-Reel Tapes
Part 2: Series III: Digital Audiotapes (DAT)
Part 2: Series IV: Archival Masters (Reel-to-Reel Tapes)
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frederic Ewen Photograph Collection (Photographs #210)
Frederic Ewen Graphics Collection (Graphics #21)
Board of Higher Education of the City of New York: Academic Freedom Cases (Tam #332)
Henry Foner Papers (Tam #254).
Frederic Ewen Papers (Tam #277)
English literature.; Communist teachers.; Communism -- United States.; Anti-communist movements.; Literature |x Study and teaching.; Digital audio tapes.; Videotapes.; Audiotapes.; New York (N.Y.); Audiocassettes.; Archival master audiotapes.; Oral histories (document genres); Buck, Paul, 1911-; Cammer, Moses; Caress, Barbara; Case, Clara; Case, Meyer; City University of New York. City College; Cohen, David.; Cunningham, Sarah.; Aron, Bruno; Auerbach, Leo, 1918-; Austin, Richard, 1903-; Schrecker, Ellen; Bander, Ingram; Baron, Ben.; Brand, Phoebe, 1907-2004; Bressler, Joseph, 1907-; Brooklyn College; Ackely, John.; Adler, Joyce Sparer.; Adler, Irving; Teachers' Union of the City of New York; Sperber, Al.; Rubinstein, Annette Teta, 1910-2007.; Steigman, Joseph, 1913-; Schappes, Morris U. (Morris Urman), 1907-; Wallach, Sam; Thomas, Sidney, 1915-; Nelson, Marjorie.; New York (State). Legislature. Joint Committee to Investigate Procedure and Methods of Allocating State Moneys for Public School Purposes and Subversive Activities; Kamin, Leon J.; Leberstein, Steven; Schaftel, Oscar.; Pomerance, Isidore.; Randolph, John, 1915-2004; Friedman, David.; Fraunglass, William.; Franklin, Norman L.; Foner, Philip Sheldon, 1910-1994; Kaiser, Samuel, 1910-; Harap, Louis; Goldway, David.; Gideon, Miriam, 1906-1996; Dunham, Barrows, 1905-; Donath, Ludwig; Dee, Ruby; Davis, Ossie; Foner, Moe, 1915-; Ewen, Alexander.; Foner, Henry; Wheeler, George Shaw, 1908-
- Series I: Interviews Relating to Rapp-Coudert Committee Investigations and Blacklisting (Audiotapes, Videotapes and Transcripts).
  - Sub-series A: Audiocassette tapes.
    - Adler, Irving - Tape 1 of 2 (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 1, 1990; cuid458 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-1, Box 16, Cd cuid458a-b)
    - Adler, Irving - Tape 2 of 2 (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 1, 1990; cuid459 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-2, Box 16, Cd cuid459)
    - Adler, Joyce (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 1, 1990; cuid460 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-3, Box 16, Cd cuid460)
    - Auerbach, Leo - Tape 1 of 2 (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 2, 1990; cuid461 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-4, Box 16, Cd cuid461a-b)
    - Auerbach, Leo - Tape 2 of 2 (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 2, 1990; cuid462 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-5, Box 16, Cd cuid462)
    - Bander, Ingram (90 minute tape), undated (Box 1, Folder OH 52-6, Box 16, Cd ref22a-b)
    - Bressler, Joe (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 16, 1990; cuid463 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-7, Box 16, Cd cuid463a-b)
    - Buck, Paul with Interviewer Ellen Schrecker - Tape 1 of 2 [tape missing], Jan 10, 1978; cuid464 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-8)
    - Buck, Paul with Interviewer Ellen Schrecker - Tape 2 of 2 (60 minute tape), Jan 10, 1978; cuid465 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-9, Box 16, Cd cuid465)
    - Cammer, Moses with Interviewers Steven Leberstein and Barbara Caress - Tape 1 of 2 (90 minute tape), May 1982; cuid466 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-10, Box 16, Cd cuid466)
    - Cammer, Moses with Interviewers Steven Leberstein and Barbara Caress - Tape 2 of 2 (90 minute tape), May 1982; cuid467 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-11, Box 16, Cd cuid467)
    - Foner, Henry (60 minute tape) Transcript Available, Mar 3, 1990; cuid468 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-12, Box 17, Cd cuid468)
    - Frauenglass, William (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 23, 1990; cuid469 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-13, Box 17, Cd cuid469)
    - Gideon, Miriam (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, Jan 12, 1990; cuid470 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-14, Box 17, Cd cuid470)
    - Goldway, David with Interviewers Steven Leberstein and Barbara Caress (90 minute tape), May 1, 1982 (Box 17, Cd ref31, Box 1, Folder OH 52-15)
    - Goldway, David with Interviewers Steven Leberstein and Barbara Caress (90 minute tape), Jun 1, 1982 (Box 17, Cd ref32, Box 1, Folder OH 52-16)
    - Harap, Louis (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 4, 1990 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-17, Box 17, Cd ref33)
    - Kaiser, Sam (90 minute tape), May 14, 1990 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-18, Box 17, Cd ref34)
    - Kamin, Leon - with Interviewer Ellen Schrecker (?) (90 minute tape), undated; cuid471 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-19, Box 17, Cd cuid471)
    - Randolph, John - Tape 1 of 2 (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 13, 1990; cuid472 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-20, Box 17, Cd cuid472a-b)
    - Randolph, John - Tape 2 of 2 (missing) Transcript Available, May 13, 1990; cuid473 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-21)
    - Schaftel, Oscar - Tape 1 of 2 (missing) Transcript Available, Apr 18, 1990; cuid474 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-22)
    - Schaftel, Oscar - Tape 2 of 2 (60 minute tape) Transcript Available, Apr 18, 1990; cuid475 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-23, Box 17, Cd cuid475)
    - Sperber, Al - Tape 1 of 2 (90 minute tape) [May need restoration.], May 15, 1990; cuid476 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-24, Box 17, Cd cuid476a-b)
    - Sperber, Al - Tape 2 of 2 (60 minute tape), May 15, 1990; cuid477 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-25, Box 17, Cd cuid477)
    - Thomas, Sidney (90 minute tape) Transcript Available, May 7, 1990; cuid478 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-26, Box 17, Cd cuid478a-b)
    - Grebanier, Bernard - CD 1 of 3 (Tape 1 Side A), April 24, 1974; cuid479 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-26.A)
    - Grebanier, Bernard - CD 2 of 3 (Tape 1 Side B), April, 24 1974; cuid480 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-26.B)
    - Grebanier, Bernard - CD 3 of 3 (Tape 2 Side A), cuid481 (Box 1, Folder OH 52-26.C)
  - Sub-series B: Hi-8 Videotapes.
    - Ackely, John Memorial (120 minute tape), Oct 25, 1990; cuid213 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V1, Box 16, Dvd cuid213)
    - Aron, Bruno (60 minute tape), undated; cuid214 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V2, Box 16, Dvd cuid214)
    - Austin, Richard (60 minute tape), undated; cuid215 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V3, Box 16, Dvd cuid215)
    - Baron, Ben - Tape 1 of 2 (60 minute tape), Jun 19, 1990; cuid216 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V4, Box 16, Dvd cuid216)
    - Baron, Ben - Tape 2 of 2 (60 minute tape), Jun 19, 1990; cuid217 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V5, Box 16, Dvd cuid217)
    - Case, Meyer and Clara (90 minute tape), undated; cuid218 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V6, Box 16, Dvd cuid218)
    - Cohen, David (120 minute tape), Nov 6, 1990; cuid219 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V7, Box 16, Dvd cuid219)
    - Dunham, Barrows - Tape 1 of 2 (60 minute tape), May 29, 1990; cuid220 (Box 16, Dvd ref51, Box 2, Folder OH-52-V8)
    - Dunham, Barrows - Tape 2 of 2 (60 minute tape), May 29, 1990; cuid221 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V9, Box 16, Dvd ref52)
    - Foner, Moe (60 minute tape), Jun 6, 1990; cuid222 (Box 2, Folder OH-52- V10, Box 16, Dvd cuid222)
    - Foner, Philip - Tape 1 of 2 (60 minute tape), Oct 3, 1990; cuid223 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V11, Box 16, Dvd cuid223)
    - Foner, Philip - Tape 2 of 2 (120 minute tape), Oct 3, 1990; cuid224 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V12, Box 16, Dvd ref55)
    - Franklin, Norman (90 minute tape), Jun 27, 1990; cuid225 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V13, Box 16, Dvd cuid225)
    - Friedman, David (60 minute tape), undated; cuid226 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V14, Box 16, Dvd cuid226)
    - Goldway, David - Tape 1 of 2 (60 minute tape) Transcript [dated May 3, 1990] available., Apr 3, 1990; cuid227 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V15, Box 16, Dvd cuid227)
    - Goldway, David - Tape 2 of 2 (60 minute tape) Transcript [dated May 3, 1990] available., Apr 3, 1990; cuid228 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V16, Box 16, Dvd cuid228)
    - Pomerance, Isidore - Tape 1 of 3 (60 minute tape), undated; cuid229 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V17, Box 16, Dvd cuid229_ntsc)
      Scope and Contents
      The original recording was split into two access DVDs during the digitization process. Original content on tape had been recorded over at some point with a Spanish Language program. Isidore interview is present on the item marked cuid229_ntsc. Additional access DVD will play Spanish Language program.
    - Pomerance, Isidore - Tape 2 of 3 (60 minute tape), undated; cuid230 (Box 16, Dvd ref61, Box 2, Folder OH-52-V18)
    - Pomerance, Isidore - Tape 3 of 3 (60 minute tape), undated; cuid231 (Box 16, Dvd ref62, Box 2, Folder OH-52-V19)
    - Schappes, Morris (120 minute tape), Nov 7, 1990; cuid232 (Box 16, Dvd ref63, Box 2, Folder OH-52-V20)
    - Sperber, Al - Tape 1 of 2 (60 minute tape), May 15, 1990; cuid233 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V21, Box 16, Dvd cuid233)
    - Sperber, Al - Tape 2 of 2 (60 minute tape), May 15, 1990; cuid234 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V22, Box 16, Dvd cuid234)
    - Steigman, Joseph (60 minute tape), May 9, 1990; cuid235 (Box 2, Folder OH-52-V23, Box 16, Dvd cuid235)
  - Sub-series C: Transcripts.
    - Adler, Irving, May 1, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Adler, Joyce, May 1, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Auerbach, Leo, May 2, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bressler, Joe, May 16, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Foner, Henry, Mar 7, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Fraunglass, William, May 23, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Gideon, Miriam, Jan 12, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Goldway, David, May 3, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Harap, Louis, May 4, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Randolph, John, May 13, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Rubenstein, Annette (No accompanying audio or videotape), undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Schaftel, Oscar, Apr 18, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Thomas, Sidney, May 7, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Wallach, Sam (No accompanying audio or videotape), May 2, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Wheeler, George (No accompanying audio or videotape), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Series II: Public Lectures and Performances (Audiotapes).
  - Poetry and the Voice of Mankind Series: Ewen lectures "Whitman - Poet of Democracy" and "William Butler Yeats and T.S. Eliot - The Poetry of Reaction" - Tape 1 of 2 (90 minute tape), Feb 15, 1954, Feb 22, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-27)
  - Poetry and the Voice of Mankind Series: Ewen lectures "Whitman - Poet of Democracy" and "William Butler Yeats and T.S. Eliot - The Poetry of Reaction" - Tape 2 of 2 (90 minute tape), Feb 15, 1954, Feb 22, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-28)
  - Poetry and the Voice of Mankind Series: Ewen lecture "Garcia Lorca and Pablo Neruda: Voices of Spain and Latin America" - Tape 1 of 2 (90 minute tape), Mar 1, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-29)
  - Poetry and the Voice of Mankind Series: Ewen lecture "Garcia Lorca and Pablo Neruda: Voices of Spain and Latin America" - Tape 2 of 2 (90 minute tape), Mar 1, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-30)
  - Poetry and the Voice of Mankind Series: Ewen lecture "Singing Tomorrows - The Poetry of Resistance and Heroism" - Tape 1 of 2 (90 minute tape), Mar 8, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-31)
  - Poetry and the Voice of Mankind Series: Ewen lecture "Singing Tomorrows - The Poetry of Resistance and Heroism" - Tape 2 of 2 (90 minute tape), Mar 8, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-32)
  - Theater of Ideas Series with lectures and dramatic readings by Ewen and actors: Euripides' The Trojan Women and Hans Chlumberg's Miracle at Verdun with Ruby Dee - Tape 1 of 2 (Performers in the series include Sarah Cunningham, Ossie Davis, Ruby Dee, Ludwig Donath and Marjorie Nelson) (90 minute tape), Oct 4, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-33)
  - Theater of Ideas Series with lectures and dramatic readings by Ewen and actors: Euripides' The Trojan Women and Hans Chlumberg's Miracle at Verdun with Ruby Dee - Tape 2 of 2 (Performers in the series include Sarah Cunningham, Ossie Davis, Ruby Dee, Ludwig Donath and Marjorie Nelson) (90 minute tape), Oct 4, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-34)
  - Theater of Ideas Series with lectures and dramatic readings by Ewen and actors: Bertolt Brecht's Galileo and August Strindberg's The Dream Play- Tape 1 of 2 (Performers in the series included Sarah Cunningham, Ossie Davis, Ruby Dee, Ludwig Donath and Marjorie Nelson) (90 minute tape), Oct 25, 1954, Nov 8, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-35)
  - Theater of Ideas Series with lectures and dramatic readings by Ewen and actors: Bertolt Brecht's Galileo and August Strindberg's The Dream Play- Tape 2 of 2 (Performers in the series included Sarah Cunningham, Ossie Davis, Ruby Dee, Ludwig Donath and Marjorie Nelson) (90 minute tape), Oct 25, 1954, Nov 8, 1954 (Box 4, Folder OH 52-36)